<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<book lang="en">
	<bookinfo>
		<title>Amun manual</title>
		<abstract>
			<para>This is the official manual of Amun.</para>
		</abstract>
	</bookinfo>

	<chapter>
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>Amun is a content managment framework written in PHP 5 and based on the PSX framework. The goal of
		Amun is to build a more federated and programmable web. This is achieved by providing an RESTful API for
		managing and distributing the content in standard formats like JSON, XML, Atom and RSS.</para>
	</chapter>

	<chapter>
		<title>Installation and Configuration</title>
		<para>To install Amun you need PHP >= 5.3 a current version of <ulink url="http://getcomposer.org/">Composer</ulink>
		and a MYSQL database. You can download the latest version of Amun at the <ulink url="http://amun-project.org/">website</ulink>.
		Amun uses composer to manage all dependencies and it has a custom plugin to install the database structure
		through composer. So before you run the install command you have to set your database connection settings
		in the configuration.php. After that you can simply install Amun with the following command:</para>
		<screen>php composer.phar install</screen>
		<para>If the database settings are wrong it is no problem simply correct them and use composer update to start the
		installation process again.</para>
		<para>During the installation you have to enter a username, password and email of the administrator account.
		After this you have to set the correct url in the configuration.php for the key "psx_url". The installation is now 
		complete and you should be able to visit the website.</para>
	</chapter>

	<chapter>
		<title>Enabling clean urls</title>
		<para>In order to activate clean urls you have to move the file public/htaccess.sample to public/.htaccess. After
		this you must set in the configuration.php the key "psx_dispatch" to an empty value "". Now you can access all
		pages without index.php/.</para>
	</chapter>

	<chapter>
		<title>Manage Amun</title>
		<para>In order to manage Amun you need an client wich connects to the Amun API. By default Amun comes with a javascript 
		based backend wich has all functionallity to configure and control your website. The endpoint url is at "index.php/workbench". 
		You can find a list of available backends at the <ulink url="http://amun-project.org/">website</ulink>.</para>

		<sect1>
			<title>Structure</title>
			<para>This section explains how the structure of the Amun CMS works.</para>
			<para>In Amun every functionality is provided via a service. The structure of the website is created
			with pages. A page refers to a service. I.e. if you create a page with the news service the page
			contains a list of news and you have the option to add new entries. Beside the service a page can
			load gadgets wich can display informations in a sidebar i.e. the latest news. Every service offers
			an REST API endpoint where it is possible to create new entries. In fact the website uses the API to 
			create or update records. The API endpoint of the news service is available at index.php/api/news.</para>
		</sect1>
	</chapter>

	<chapter>
		<title>3rd party applications</title>
		<para>Amun uses some 3rd party libraries and applications. Thx to all the developers
		for making such great software!</para>
		<orderedlist numeration="upperroman">
		<title>A list of all 3rd party applications used by Amun in alphabetical order.</title>
		<listitem>
			<para>Ace: <ulink url="http://ace.ajax.org/">http://ace.ajax.org/</ulink></para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Bootstrap CSS Framework: <ulink url="http://getbootstrap.com/">http://getbootstrap.com</ulink></para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Composer: <ulink url="http://getcomposer.org">http://getcomposer.org</ulink></para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>ExtJs: <ulink url="http://www.sencha.com/products/extjs">http://www.sencha.com/products/extjs</ulink></para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Google Code Prettify: <ulink url="http://code.google.com/p/google-code-prettify/">http://code.google.com/p/google-code-prettify</ulink></para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>jQuery: <ulink url="http://jquery.com">http://jquery.com</ulink></para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Monolog: <ulink url="https://github.com/Seldaek/monolog">https://github.com/Seldaek/monolog</ulink></para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>PSX: <ulink url="http://phpsx.org">http://phpsx.org</ulink></para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Zend Mail: <ulink url="http://framework.zend.com/manual/2.0/en/modules/zend.mail.introduction.html">http://framework.zend.com/manual/2.0/en/modules/zend.mail.introduction.html</ulink></para>
		</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</chapter>

	<chapter>
		<title>Help</title>
		<para>Amun is currently in an early stage so the documentation is very sparse. If you need help you
		have the followign options.</para>
		<orderedlist numeration="upperroman">
		<title>Things you can do if you have any problems with Amun</title>
		<listitem>
			<para>Join the IRC channel #phpsx on freenode</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Write an issue to the <ulink url="https://github.com/k42b3/amun/issues">bugtracker</ulink></para>
		</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</chapter>

</book>

